"Look at me!"
انظر إلي
That phrase turned me into an eye-contact coach.
هذه الجملة جعلتني مدربة في التواصل البصري.
I'm the mother of Ivan; he's 15 years old.
انا والدة ايفان البالغ من العمر 15 عامأ.
Ivan has autism,
ايفان يعاني من التوحد، ولا يتكلم،
and he communicates through an iPad,
ولكن يتواصل مع الغير عبر جهاز الايباد,
where his whole universe of words exists in images.
حيث تكمن جميع الكلمات بالنسبة له علي هيئة صور.
He was diagnosed when he was two and a half.
لقد تم تشخيصه عندما بلغ عامين ونصف.
I still remember that day painfully.
ما زلت أتذكر هذا اليوم بألم.
My husband and I felt really lost;
لقد شعرنا أنا وزوجي حينها بالضياع،
we didn't know where to begin.
لم نعرف من أين نبدأ.
There was no internet,
لم يوجد إنترنت وقتها
you couldn't Google information,
, لم نستطع البحث عن معلومات عن المرض
so we made those first steps
لذا جميع خطواتنا في البداية
out of sheer intuition.
كانت نابعه من الحدس.
Ivan would not maintain eye contact,
لم يستطع ايفان النظر في العين مباشرة،
he had lost the words that he did know,
لقد فقد الكلمات التي كان قد حفظها،
and he didn't respond to his name or to anything we asked him,
ولم يعد يستجيب عند سماع اسمه
as if words were noise.
كما لو أن الكلمات أصبحت ضوضاء بالنسبة له.
The only way I could know
لم استطع معرفة ما ألمَ
what he felt,
أو ما كان يشعر به
was looking him in the eye.
إلا بالنظر في عينيه مباشرةً.
But that bridge was broken.
ولكن حتي هذا انقطعت السبل إليه.
How could I teach him about life?
كيف يمكنني تعليمه دروس الحياة؟
When I did things he liked, he would look at me,
عندما كنت أفعل شيء يعجبه كان ينظر إلي
So I dedicated myself to working with him on those things,
لذا كرست نفسي للعمل على تطوير هذا الأمر،
so we would have more and more eye-contact moments.
ليصبح لدينا المزيد من الاتصال عبر النظر.
We would spend hours and hours playing tag with his older sister, Alexia,
كنا نمضي ساعات في لعب الغميضة مع اخته اليكسيا،
and when we said: "I caught you!"
وعندما كنت أقول"أمسكت بك!"
he would look around for us,
كان يبدأ بالبحث عنا،
and at that moment, I could feel he was alive.
وفيه هذه اللحظه أحسست أانه حي.
We also hold a record for hours spent in a swimming pool.
يمكنه أيضاً كسر الرقم القياسي في عدد الساعات التي يقضيها في حمام السباحة.
Ivan always had a passion for water.
لطالما أحب الماء.
I remember when he was two and a half,
أتذكر عندما كان عمره عامين ونصف،
on a rainy winter day,
واليوم ممطر في الشتاء،
I was taking him to an indoor pool,
كنت اصطحبه إلى لحمام سباحة مغطى،
because even on rainy days we'd go swimming.
لأنه حتى في الأيام الممطرة كان يحب الذهاب للسباحه.
We were on the highway, and I took the wrong exit.
كنا علي الطريق السريع وسلكت المخرج الخاطئ.
He burst into tears and cried inconsolably, nonstop,
أجهش بالبكاء وظل يبكي دون توقف
until I turned back.
إلا عندما عدت أدراجي مجدداً،
Only then did he calm down.
عندها فقط توقف عن البكاء.
How was it possible that a two and a half year old
كيف يمكن لطفل في الثانية والنصف من العمر
didn't respond to his own name,
ألا يستجيب لاسمه ومع ذلك
yet in the middle of the rain and fog, where I couldn't see anything,
في وجود المطر والضباب عندما لم استطع رؤية أي شيء
he knew the exact route?
تمكن هو من معرفة الطريق ؟
That's when I realized that Ivan had an exceptional visual memory,
حينها أدركت أن لدى ايفان ذاكرة بصرية قوية،
and that that would be my way in.
وأن هذا سيكون سبيلي للوصول إليه.
So I started taking pictures of everything,
لذا بدأت بالتقاط صوراً لكل شئ،
and teaching him what life was like,
وتعليمه ما هي الحياة،
Even now, it's the way Ivan communicates
حتي الآن هذه طريقته في التواصل،
what he wants,
ما يريده،
what he needs
وما يحتاجه،
and also what he feels.
وما يشعربه أيضاً.
But it wasn't just Ivan's eye contact that mattered.
ولكن لم يكن المهم فقط التواصل مع ايفان بالنظر،
Everyone else's did, too.
ولكن تواصل الغير معه أيضاً.
How could I make people see not only his autism,
كيف يمكنني أن أجعل الناس ترى أكثر من التوحد الذي يعانيه،
but see him the person
ولكن رؤيته كشخص
and everything he can give;
وكل ما يستطيع اعطاؤه،
everything he can do;
ورؤية كل ما يستطيع فعله،
the things he likes and doesn't like,
وما يحب وما يكره،
just like any one of us?
تماماً كالجميع؟
But for that, I also had to give of myself.
لتحقيق ذلك كان علي أن أتنازل قليلا،
I had to have the strength to let him go,
واستجمع الشجعة لأتركه
which was extremely difficult.
وهو الأمر الذي كان في غاية الصعوبة.
Ivan was 11 years old,
عندما بلغ ايفان الحادية عشر،
and he went for treatment in a neighborhood near our house.
كان يذهب للعلاج في مركز قريب من البيت.
One afternoon, while I was waiting for him,
في أحد الأمسيات عندما كنت في انتظار عودته،
I went into a greengrocer,
ذهبت لمحل البقالة،
a typical neighborhood store with a little bit of everything.
كان متجراً عادياً كغيره يبيع القليل من هذا وذاك.
While doing the shopping,
وبينما كنت أتبضع،
I started talking to Jose, the owner.
بدأت بالتكلم مع خوسيه -مالك المتجر.
I told him about Ivan,
وأخبرته عن ايفان،
that he had autism,
وأنه يعاني من التوحد،
and that I wanted him to learn to walk down the street by himself,
وكم وددت أن أراه يمشي في الطريق بمفرده،
without anyone holding his hand.
من دون وجود أحد ليمسك يده.
So I decided to ask Jose if Thursdays around 2pm,
لذا سألت خوسيه إذا كان الخميس في الثانيه بعد الظهر
Ivan could come and help him arrange the water bottles on the shelves,
وقتا مناسبا لارسال ايفان لمساعدته في رص زجاجات المياه فوق الارفف
because he loved to organize things.
لأنه كان يحب تنظيم الأشياء.
And as a reward, he could buy some chocolate cookies,
وكمكافأه له يمكنه شراء بعض بسكويت الشوكولاته،
which were his favorite.
لأنها المفضلة لديه.
He said "yes" right away.
وافق خوسيه علي الفور.
So that's how it went for a year:
لذا استمر الأمر لمدة عام؛
Ivan would go to Jose's greengrocer,
كان يذهب ايفان لمحل خوسيه
help him arrange the shelves of water bottles
ويساعده في تنظيم أرفف زجاجات المياه
with the labels perfectly lined up on the same side,
بوضع الملصقات مصطفة بشكل مثالي على نفس الجانب
and he would leave happy with his chocolate cookies.
وكان يغادر بسعادة وفي حوزته المكافأه.
Jose is not an expert in autism.
لم يكن خوسيه خبيراً في التوحد.
There is no need to be an expert
لست بحاجة أن تكون خبيراً،
nor do anything heroic to include someone.
أو تقوم بأي عمل بطولي لتدخل عالمه.
We just need to be there --
كل ما نحتاجه هو أن نتواجد بجانبه.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Applause ends)
(انتهاء التصفيق)
Really, no heroic deed --
حقا لا عمل بطولي،
we simply need to be close.
ببساطة يجب أن نكون قريبين.
And if we are afraid of something
وإذا كنا خائفين من شيء ما،
or we don't understand something,
أو لا نستطيع فهم شيء ما،
we need to ask.
علينا أن نسأل.
Let's be curious
لنكن فضوليّين
but never indifferent.
والابتعاد عن اللامبالاة.
Let's have the courage to look each other in the eye,
لتكن لدينا الشجاعه للنظر في أعين بعض مباشرة،
because by looking,
لأنه بالنظر
we can open a whole world to someone else.
يمكننا فتح عالماً كاملاً لشخص آخر.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)